Good morning, this is Dan Magid subbing in for Rabbi Linzer while
he's away. Today is the 6th of אדר, Adar, March 16th, and
we are going to be starting on קידושין Kiddushin דף ד Daf
Dalet towards the bottom of עמוד ב, Amud Bet, going into דף
ה. Daf He.
So we are starting sort of in the middle of a topic,
which is the questions of on the one hand what are the
לימודים, limudim, what are the derivations for each of the three different
ways of getting married, that is כסף, kesef, שטר, shtar, and ביאה,
biah, and the גמרא Gemara has already brought most of the proofs
for קידושי כסף kidushei kesef and has already gotten into the discussion
of קידושי ביאה. kidushei biah. Interestingly enough the order is different in
the דרשות drashot in the גמרא Gemara than it is in the
משנה. Mishnah. The משנה Mishnah goes כסף, kesef, שטר, shtar, and then
ביאה, biah, and in the גמרא Gemara שטר shtar is last. We're
going to deal with that today. And we have this last paragraph
here on the bottom of ד עמוד ב, Dalet Amud Bet, ובעלה.
uv'alah. The word ובעלה uv'alah in the פסוק pasuk that is, the
פסוק pasuk says, כי יקח איש אשה ובעלה, ki yikach ish isha
uv'alah, when a man takes a wife and בעלה ba'alah becomes her
בעל, ba'al, perhaps in a more graphic sense is an active verb,
but ובעלה מלמד שנקנית בביאה. uv'alah melamed sheniknet b'biah. So the word
ובעלה uv'alah teaches that the קנין kinyan of קידושין kiddushin is effected
through a sexual act, and it's important to note the גמרא Gemara
later on in a few דפים dappim is going to ask the
question, an important question, which is ביאה קידושין עושה או ביאה נישואין
עושה? biah kiddushin oseh o biah nissuin oseh? Does that initial sexual
act do both stages of marriage at once?
Can you jump across both קידושין kiddushin and נישואין nissuin in that
way, or will it only affect קידושין kiddushin and you'll need a
second step in order to effect נישואין nissuin as well? Recording it
on this. Oh was that the wrong... oh well, sorry. Wrong recorder,
but it is being recorded. It says microphone etc. I didn't
mean to do it on that. Okay. ובעלה מלמד שנקנית בביאה, uv'alah
melamed sheniknet b'biah, doesn't it... isn't it obvious? Isn't it derivable from
different דרשות drashot from קל וחומר kal vachomer and we would not
need the word ובעלה? uv'alah?
So the question אינו דין, aino din, sorry... והלא דין הוא, v'halo
din hu, ומה יבמה שאינה נקנית בכסף נקנית בביאה,
u'ma yevama she'eina
niknet b'kesef niknet b'biah, just like a
יבמה yevama can be acquired through sexual act, that is the משנה
Mishnah had listed that ייבום yibbum is effected only through sex, however
ייבום yibbum cannot be effected through money, זו שנקנית בכסף אינו דין
שנקנית בביאה, zu sheniknet b'kesef aino din sheniknet b'biah,
then in a normal marriage, not ייבום, yibbum, which we know can
be effected through money, doesn't that show us that money is more
generally applicable and therefore ביאה biah should also work by קל וחומר?
kal vachomer? We're going to see that the גמרא Gemara continually compares
and contrasts three different cases of marriage: ייבום, yibbum, אמה עברית, amah
ivriya, and normal marriage. ייבום yibbum is a case where the brother-in-law
has passed away without children and his wife is already in some
sense married to her brother-in-law, but they have to still consummate that
relationship anyway and that's the קנין kinyan of ייבום yibbum and it's
a מצוה mitzvah or it could be dissolved through חליצה. chalitzah. The
אמה עברית amah ivriya that we're going to note is somewhat marital
and somewhat not. The גמרא Gemara insists that it is not marital,
but if we read the פסוקים pesukim and we'll see תוספות Tosafot
make a big deal about the fact that אמה עברית, amah ivriya,
that is when a minor girl is sold off as an indentured
servant by her father, while it's primarily about her labor, it actually
does have elements of a marital relationship as well, and we're going
to see that. Okay, so those different cases are all connected by
these קל וחומרs. kal vachomer Also, the three different ways of getting
married are all going to be compared and interchanged with each other
and also comparing קידושין kiddushin and גירושין, gerushin, that is the היקש
הוויה ליציאה,
hekkesh
havayah l'yitziah, we're going to see that there are comparisons between them
as well. And the question is when we put all three of
those different types of לימודים limudim together in a blender, which ones
come out on top? That is, which comparisons and which connections are
primary and which are secondary? And this really gets to the core
issues about what is the institution of קידושין kiddushin and how is
it effected and how are each of these different elements playing into
this. זו שנקנית בכסף אינו דין שנקנית בביאה, zu sheniknet b'kesef aino
din sheniknet b'biah, אמה עברית תוכיח. amah ivriya tochiach.
So just like we brought a question, we tried to make a
קל וחומר kal vachomer from יבמה, yevama, so אמה עברית amah ivriya
undermines that קל וחומר, kal vachomer, שנקנית בכסף ואין נקנית בביאה, sheniknet
b'kesef v'ein niknet b'biah, you cannot transfer the right... So just like
we brought a question, we tried to make a קל וחומר kal
vachomer from יבמה, yevamah, so אמה העבריה amah ha-ivriyah undermines that קל
וחומר kal vachomer שנקנית בכסף ואינה נקנית בביאה. shenikneit be-chesef ve-einah nikneit
be-viah. You cannot transfer the rights to an אמה העבריה's amah ha-ivriyah
labor through ביאה. bi-ah. מה לאמה העבריה שכן קניינה לשום אישות. mah
le-amah ha-ivriyah sheken kinyanah leshum ishut.
So the גמרא gemara says אמה העבריה amah ha-ivriyah is not a
marital relationship. So תאמר בזו שקניינה לשום אישות, tomar be-zo she-kinyanah leshum
ishut, so can we then compare it to both יבמה yevamah and
regular marriage which are לשום אישות, leshum ishut, that are marital? תלמוד
לומר ובעלה talmud lomar u-va'alah and that's why we need the פסוק
pasuk to use the word ובעלה u-va'alah to teach us that a
normal marriage could be effected through sex. Wait, why?
Meaning we just said אמה העבריה, amah ha-ivriyah, we tried to undermine
it by אמה העבריה, amah ha-ivriyah, we said אמה העבריה amah ha-ivriyah
it doesn't undermine it, and then we're left with the same קל
וחומר. kal vachomer.
No, meaning the קל וחומר, kal vachomer, the problem of the קל
וחומר kal vachomer is that... sorry. מה לי אמה העבריה שאין קניינה
לשום אישות תאמר בזו שקניינה לשום אישות. mah li amah ha-ivriyah she-ein
kinyanah leshum ishut tomar be-zo she-kinyanah leshum ishut.
So we're saying that אמה העבריה... amah ha-ivriyah... ah, no, sorry, I'm
sorry. ובעלה ולמה לי קרא הא אתיא לה? u-va'alah ve-lamah li kra
ha atya lah?
Because we're saying exactly that point, that we don't need the פסוק
ובעלה. pasuk u-va'alah. אמר רב אשי משום דאיכא למימר מעיקרא דדינא פירכא
מהיכא קא מייתי לה מיבמה מה ליבמה שכן זקוקה ועומדת. amar rav
ashi mishum de-ika le-meimar me-ikara de-dina pircha me-heicha ka maitye lah mi-yevamah
mah li-yevamah sheken zekukah ve-omedet.
So now רב אשי rav ashi has to come along and reject
the rejection, that is to prove why we do need ובעלה, u-va'alah,
and he says יבמה yevamah also cannot be extended to apply to
normal marriage, that is יבמה, yevamah, ייבום yibum is different from marriage
which is different than אמה העבריה. amah ha-ivriyah. They're all three distinct
kinds of cases. Because רב אשי rav ashi says מה ליבמה שכן
זקוקה ועומדת תאמר בזו שאין זקוקה ועומדת תלמוד לומר ובעלה. mah li-yevamah
sheken zekukah ve-omedet tomar be-zo she-ein zekukah ve-omedet talmud lomar u-va'alah.
The difference between ייבום yibum and regular marriage is that in ייבום,
yibum, the יבמה yevamah is considered זקוקה ועומדת. zekukah ve-omedet. That state
of what we call זיקה, zikah, that is the state after her
husband has died and before she has done either חליצה chalitzah or
ייבום yibum with the יבם, yavam, that זיקה zikah is in some
sense already stronger or sets the stage in a way, enables the
process to continue more than a normal marriage where there's nothing setting
the stage already. It's interesting to consider according to some of the
תנאים, tanna'im, even I think רבי עקיבא's Rabbi Akiva opinion is important
in this, I don't remember the סוגיא sugya exactly, but that the
זיקה, zikah, there's already a מחלוקת יש זיקה או אין זיקה. machloket
yesh zikah o ein zikah. It's a מחלוקת תנאים. machloket tanna'im. And
the question of how much when we say זיקה, zikah, is that
זיקה zikah comparable to קידושין kidushin almost? That is, the act of
ייבום yibum maybe taking this marriage from a somewhat מקודשת mekudeshet state
and already completing the third stage towards נישואין. nisu'in. Mike,
do you have a question? No. Oh, okay, sorry.
So the תוספות tosafot towards the bottom on דף ד עמוד ב
daf daled amud bet gets into some of those questions of אמה
העבריה, amah ha-ivriyah, and it's important to note that אמה העבריה, amah
ha-ivriyah, one of the rights of the master—it's not exactly a slavery
kind of case, it's an indentured servitude case, this young woman or
really girl has been indentured to work until she comes of age—but
one of the rights reserved by the master is ייעוד. ye'ud. ייעוד
ye'ud means that he can marry her to himself or he can
marry her to his son, and the כסף קידושין kesef kidushin is
retroactively part of the כסף kesef that was granted at the time
of the slave purchase. That is, ייעוד ye'ud is a marital aspect
of אמה העבריה, amah ha-ivriyah, and so while the גמרא gemara has
rejected the notion of אמה העבריה שאינה לשום אישות, amah ha-ivriyah she-einah
leshum ishut,
nonetheless תוספות tosafot brings in this problem of what else is going
on with אמה העבריה amah ha-ivriyah regarding ייעוד ye'ud that maybe it
really is more marital, and there are a number of other points
in תוספות tosafot that maybe we don't really have enough time to
go into. Let's go on to דף ה daf hey where we're
getting into the question of שטר. shtar. ומניין שאף בשטר? u-minayin she-af
be-shtar? The interesting
thing that the גמרא gemara uses the word אף af also, right?
This order notes that שטר shtar is perhaps the least intuitive way
to get married, and we're going to see perhaps some of the
reasons why throughout the גמרא. gemara. So ומניין שאף בשטר? u-minayin she-af
be-shtar? How do we know that marriage, that is קידושין, kidushin, could
be effected by giving a שטר, shtar, that is some kind of
a document?
ודין הוא, ve-din hu, isn't it a קל וחומר? kal vachomer? You
see the common structure of all these סוגיות sugyot is to first
suggest a קל וחומר kal vachomer from one of the other types
of marriage, to reject the קל וחומר, kal vachomer, and to introduce
an independent לימוד. limud. After we complete all three, then there'll be
an attempt to learn from two to learn out the third one.
That is, if we can't learn one by one, maybe we can
try to do צד השווה שבהן tzad ha-shaveh she-bahen and we're going
to see that on עמוד ב. amud bet.
But the underlying principle in the entire סוגיא sugya is that it
would be preferable to learn from a קל וחומר kal vachomer and
not use a scriptural reference for this, and use it for something
else.
Exactly. And that's our general operating principle throughout. That is, if we
can learn, particularly קל וחומר kal vachomer which does not require us
to use up any פסוקים pesukim or any דרשות, drashot, it would
be most expedient, most efficient if we could learn things by קל
וחומר. kal vachomer. So let's see the גמרא: gemara: ומניין שאף בשטר
ודין הוא מה כסף שאין מוציא מכניס. u-minayin she-af be-shtar ve-din hu
mah kesef she-ein motzi machnis. Money, which can be used to enter
into a marriage but cannot be used to effect divorce, that is
אין מוציא. ein motzi. כסף, Kesef, you cannot give כסף kesef for
divorce. We spent three months learning מסכת גיטין. Masechet Gittin. A גט
get can only be given as
a document, ספר כריתות ואין דבר אחר כריתות. sefer keritut ve'ein davar
acher keritut. We're going to see that דרשה drasha today.
So, מה כסף שאין מוציא מכניס, שטר שמוציא אינו דין שמכניס? ma
kesef she'ein motzi machnis, shtar shemotzi eino din shemachnis? Isn't it by
קל וחומר kal vachomer that since we know that a שטר shtar
can end a marriage, perhaps a שטר shtar could begin the marriage?
Then say ביאה biah which is אינו מוציא. eino motzi.
Ah, but we're trying to learn...
but this is ridiculous.
So one second. Is it ridiculous though to say the power of
a שטר shtar is so powerful that the שטר shtar can even
end the marriage?
So ביאה biah is so powerful it can begin the marriage, but
surely it can't end the marriage.
But that doesn't make sense. That's not powerful.
That's the point.
So this part of the question, the רשב"א Rashba frames this in
the context of כוח דהיתרא עדיף, koach deheteira adif, the strength necessary
to create permissibility, that is the strength of the גט, get, is
a stronger power than to create a prohibition. We have principles where
you can make איסורים issurim all over the place. We have נדרים,
nedarim, we have the principle שוויא אנפשיה כחתיכה דאיסורא. shavei anafshei kachaticha
de'issura. So those are all principles whereby a prohibition can be introduced
with relative ease. But to create a leniency where there is none,
to create permission where there is none, is impossible. You can't make
something מותר mutar that is already אסור. assur. That's the power of
a גט, get, so obviously a גט, get, a שטר, shtar, has
incredible legal weight. We know that שטרות shtarot in the monetary realm
as well have incredible power in terms of their
reliability in court. רבי יוחנן's Rabbi Yochanan opinion, עדים החתומים על השטר
נעשו כמי שנחקרה עדותם בבית דין, edim hachatumim al hashtar na'asu kemi
shenechkera edutam beveit din, that the witnesses who have signed on the
שטר shtar do not need to undergo the דרישה וחקירה drisha vechakira
in the same way that witnesses who come in person for a
court case; they're already automatically accepted. So a שטר shtar really is
a powerful thing or almost magical thing in the הלכה Halacha that
it really is incredibly robust. So here too we see that the
strength of the שטר shtar to effect divorce is actually incredibly powerful,
particularly the fact that it creates a היתר heter where there would
have been a severe איסור. issur.
I understand you're comparing it to כסף. kesef. You're saying it's a
קל וחומר kal vachomer from כסף. kesef.
So it's no, it's a קל וחומר kal vachomer from שטר. shtar.
That is, the point is when you compare שטר shtar to כסף,
kesef, כסף kesef we know can make a marriage. And we don't
know whether שטר shtar can make a marriage or not. We know
שטר shtar can end a marriage. The fact that שטר shtar can
end a marriage is a unique power, is incredibly strong, so it
sounds like we should also be able to derive that שטר... shtar...
now this is not going to be the exact לימוד limmud right
now, but that's the suggestion. Okay, so מה לכסף שכן פודים בו
הקדש ומעשר שני. ma lakesef sheken podim bo hekdesh uma'aser sheni. But
what about כסף? kesef? כסף, kesef, unlike שטר, shtar, could be used
for פדיון, pidyon, that is to transfer the state of either מעשר
שני ma'aser sheni or הקדש, hekdesh, which normally would have to be
brought to ירושלים Yerushalayim and brought either as קרבנות korbanot or eaten
in ירושלים, Yerushalayim, and the money could be used to redeem those
statuses onto the money and to bring the money to ירושלים Yerushalayim
and buy other things.
So what, was it גירושין gerushin and קידושין?
kiddushin? One second. That's exactly part of the question, which is how
far a net are we casting when we talk about status changes.
If I have a pile of fruit and it's מעשר שני ma'aser
sheni and I want to be פודה podeh מעשר שני ma'aser sheni
onto a silver coin, that status change in some sense is similar
to קידושין kiddushin in that, again, we've already seen the comparison or
equation between קידושין kiddushin and הקדש. hekdesh. דאסר לה אכולי עלמא כהקדש,
de'assar lah achulei alma kehekdesh, we have on ב ע"ב. bet amud
bet. The fact that the לשון lashon קידושין, kiddushin, the use of
the word קידושין kiddushin is to compare the marital act in some
sense, both the prohibitions of the marital act as well as the
sanctity of the marital union to הקדש hekdesh in some sense. So
we should be able to at least in some sense compare the
act of פדיון pidyon to marriage. Now again, also the question is
פדיון pidyon is not exactly monetary. It's dealing with איסורים, issurim, it's
dealing with something which is consecrated property. And thus the type of
status that's being affected and changed is in some sense comparable. Now
this is going to be rejected, but it's important to note the
unique power of כסף kesef here. The פסוק pasuk says, it's not
exactly a פסוק, pasuk, we're going to see the גמרא Gemara quotes
ונתן הכסף וקם לו venatan hakesef vekam lo is actually two different
פסוקים pesukim smushed together, but it's what's always used to quote the
fact that you can use money to be פודה, podeh, to redeem
your מעשר שני. ma'aser sheni. ונתן הכסף וקם לו, venatan hakesef vekam
lo, the fact that money can absorb the status of מעשר שני
ma'aser sheni is a unique quality of money unlike any other קניין.
kinyan. רש"י Rashi suggests what kind of a שטר shtar is the
הוה אמינא? hava amina? What kind of שטר shtar would be suggested
to be used for מעשר שני? ma'aser sheni? A שטר חוב. shtar
chov. You say, 'this fruit, I'll be פודה podeh this fruit onto
this silver coin.' I don't have the silver coin with me. I
write a שטר shtar that says, 'I'm obligated to bring five dollars
silver coin to ירושלים Yerushalayim for מעשר שני.' ma'aser sheni. That would
be a שטר חוב, shtar chov, right? Creating a lien on your
own property. And the רשב"א Rashba is very upset by that, and
the רשב"א Rashba says it's not comparable. The שטר קידושין shtar kiddushin
is not A שטר shtar *shtar* of a גט get. *get* is
not a שטר shtar חוב *shtar chov*. It's a שטר shtar קניין
kinyan *shtar kinyan*. It's a שטר shtar, *shtar* that says in it
what you're doing. And the רשב״א *Rashba* suggests it would be a
שטר shtar *shtar* that just says הרי פירות אלו פדוים בשטר זו
*Harei perot elu peduyim b'shtar zo*. What פסוק pasuk *pasuk* is this?
Is it a פסוק pasuk *pasuk*?
It's from two different פסוקים pesukim. *pesukim* from ויקרא *Vayikra*, it's kind
of smushed together, ויקרא כ״ז *Vayikra Chaf-Zayin*. Okay. ונתן venatan, הכסף וקם
לו *V'natan hakesef v'kam lo*. אמר קרא amar kra, *Amar kra* ויצאה
והייתה *V'yatza v'hayta*. So the פסוק pasuk *pasuk* about divorce and marriage
connect. ויצאה *V'yatza*, she leaves, והייתה לאיש אחר *V'hayta l'ish acher*, and
she can remarry. That is after a divorce a woman can remarry.
מקיש הויה ליציאה havaya liyetziah *Makish havaya l'yetziah*. No, so we learn
it out not from some kind of קל וחומר kal v'chomer *kal
vachomer* from קידושי כסף kiddushei kesef? *kidushei kesef*, but from the היקש
*hekesh*, the connection between the act of divorce and the act of
marriage. That is מקיש הויה ליציאה *Makish havaya l'yetziah*: מה יציאה בשטר
אף הויה נמי בשטר *Mah yetziah b'shtar af havaya nami b'shtar*. Just
like you can get divorced by a גט get *get*, so too
a person could get married using a שטר קידושין shtar kiddushin *shtar
kiddushin*. So we have a question: ואיקיש נמי יציאה להויה *V'ikish nami
yetziah l'havaya*? Couldn't we make the היקש *hekesh* in the opposite direction?
That is learn from קידושין kiddushin *kiddushin* to גירושין gerushin, *gerushin*? מה
הויה בכסף אף יציאה בכסף *Mah havaya b'kesef af yetziah b'kesef*? So
just like a person can get married with money, so too you
could get divorced with money. אמר אביי Abaye *Amar Abaye*: יאמרו כסף
kesef. מכניס כסף kesef, מוציא *Yomru kesef machnis kesef motzi*. If you
would say in a world where money could be used to enter
into marriage as well as get divorced, סניגור יעשה קטיגור *Sanigor ya'aseh
katigor*. Then the defense attorney will have turned into the prosecuting attorney.
That is that the way of entering into the marriage will have
become a way of leaving the marriage. Interesting to note, this is
something Rabbi Linzer touched on before, the reality is seeping through here,
that is that קידושי כסף kiddushei kesef, *kidushei xesef* is the most
common, perhaps really only method of קידושין kiddushin *kiddushin* that חז״ל *Chazal*
are familiar with. קידושי שטר kiddushei shtar. *kidushei shtar* is not common
or is not ever really practiced and therefore there's no suspicion or
no concern that people will say סניגור יעשה קטיגור *Sanigor ya'aseh katigor*
by שטר קידושין shtar kiddushin. *shtar kiddushin*. שטר shtar? קידושין kiddushin. *Shtar
kiddushin* exists almost entirely as a theoretical construct. אי הכי שטר shtar,
נמי יאמרו שטר shtar מוציא שטר shtar מכניס *Ei hachi shtar nami
yomru shtar motzi shtar machnis*? Wait, couldn't they say the same thing?
That is if you can get married with a שטר shtar *shtar*
then you would get divorced with a שטר shtar *shtar*? קטיגור יעשה
סניגור *Katigor ya'aseh sanigor*. And that would be that the
prosecuting attorney has turned into the defense attorney by the fact that
you've made this היקש הויה ליציאה hekesh havaya liyetziah. *hekesh havaya l'yetziah*.
מילי דהאי שטרא לחוד ומילי דהאי שטרא לחוד *Milei d'hai shtar l'chod
u'milei d'hai shtar l'chod*. These are two different שטרות shtarot *shtarot*. The
answer, yeah, the words in the שטר shtar. *shtar* are different. So
that is fine, no one's going to confuse a גט get. *get*
with a שטר shtar קידושין kiddushin *shtar kiddushin* because the שטרות shtarot.
*shtarot* themselves have explicitly in the words of the שטר shtar *shtar*
what the purpose of the שטר shtar *shtar* is. No one will
confuse them.
And therefore you need a פסוק pasuk *pasuk* to prove שטר shtar
*shtar* and you can't just derive it logically?
No, it can be derived, it can be derived logically from divorce
to marriage and there's no concern of people being upset or people
being confused by קטיגור יעשה סניגור *katigor ya'aseh sanigor*. That is because
the שטרות *shtarot* are different and explicitly different, no one will say
that the way you get married is the same way you get
divorced. It's the same mechanism but a unique unique
object.
So I think also what confused me was does that דרשה drasha,
*drasha* on the פסוק pasuk *pasuk* of הויה ליציאה *havaya l'yetziah* is
considered to be a קל וחומר kal v'chomer *kal vachomer*? It's considered
to be a היקש *hekesh*.
Ah, considered to be a...
my question
is it's a היקש *hekesh* but from within the language of a
פסוק pasuk *pasuk*. Correct. So is it a לימוד limud, *limud* from
מקרא *mikra* or is it a logical construct?
Ah, so that's exactly a good question. When the רמב״ם *Rambam*, we
know, categorizes הלכות *halachot* which are learned from דרשות drashot
*drashot* differently from הלכות *halachot* which are explicit in the פסוקים *pesukim*.
רמב״ם *Rambam* will only quote as a מצווה *mitzvah* something which is
explicit in the פסוקים *pesukim* at least according to what satisfies his
criteria. The רמב״ם *Rambam*, it can be shown through his various works,
his approach to קידושין kiddushin? *kiddushin*, the three different ways of getting
married evolved over time. In the first edition of the פירוש המשנה
*Peirush Hamishnah*, the רמב״ם *Rambam* thought that only קידושי ביאה kiddushei biah
*kidushei biah* was what he would call a דאורייתא *de'oraita*, that is
explicit in the פסוק pasuk *pasuk*, and both שטר shtar *shtar* and
כסף kesef *kesef* were learned out from דרשות *drashot*. In second edition
of the פירוש המשנה *Peirush Hamishnah* and in the first edition of
the משנה Mishnah תורה Torah *Mishneh Torah*, he says that שטר shtar
*shtar* and ביאה biah *biah* are דאורייתא *de'oraita* and כסף kesef. *kesef*
is what he calls דברי סופרים *divrei sofrim* which is means it's
learned from a דרשה drasha *drasha*. And by the time he re-edited
משנה Mishna. תורה Torah *Mishneh Torah* later in life, the as if
second edition משנה Mishna תורה *Mishneh Torah*, he had changed it and
this is recorded in the תשובות *teshuvot* of his son רבי אברהם
בן הרמב״ם *Rabbi Avraham ben haRambam* that he says שלשתן דבר תורה
*shloshtan d'var Torah*, all three are considered to be דאורייתא *de'oraita*. So
the רמב״ם *Rambam*'s understanding of how the דרשות *drashot* apply to קידושין
kiddushin? *kiddushin* to the each of the three different methods of קידושין
kiddushin? *kiddushin* is very interesting but obviously he sees the word ובעלה
*u've'alah* literally... פסוקים that are made by either the question of שדה
עפרון Sdei Ephron or אמה העבריה. amah ha'ivriyah. So Rambam was willing
to change his mind? Of course he was willing to change—everyone is
willing to change their mind. The question is when you have a
contradiction between two different Rambams, what do you go by? Right? That's
the question. Right. Okay. So we said, so מילי דהאי שטר לחווד
מילי דהאי שטר לחווד, miley dehai shtar lachud miley dehai shtar lachud,
the two different שטרות are unique. הכא נמי האי כספא לחווד האי
כספא לחווד, hacha nami hai kaspa lachud hai kaspa lachud, so shouldn't
we also say the money that's used for קידושין kiddushin will be
different coins than the money that's used for divorce, if we would
live in a world where divorce was possible through money? So טיבעא
מחד הוא, tiba michad hu, no, because money all has the same
nature. That is, coins are fungible. A שטר shtar is a unique
object. If I have a five-dollar bill, I have no care in
the world that this five-dollar bill is different from any other five-dollar
bill. If I lose a five-dollar bill or someone steals a five-dollar
bill from me, all I want is five dollars back. I don't
care that it's the exact object. So that's the difference between a
שטר shtar. and כסף. kesef That is, כסף, kesef the whole nature
of כסף kesef is טיבעא מחד הוא. tiba michad hu. It has
one nature. And that is that even if you
would get married with money and divorced with money, then people would
still be able to say well
you're doing the same, the same money. But if you get married
with a שטר shtar and divorced with a שטר, shtar, they're two
unique, two different unique שטרות. Some people would say you get married
or divorced with money. So we don't, we have this general principle:
אין קטיגור נעשה סניגור. ein kategor na'aseh sanegor. We apply it to
the שופר shofar on ראש השנה. Rosh Hashanah. We don't use a
cow's horn for the שופר, shofar, even though sort of at a
technical level perhaps it would be appropriate. The כהן גדול Kohen Gadol
does not wear gold into the קודש קודשים Kodesh Kodashim on יום
כיפור. Yom Kippur. The idea that somehow things from which we've sinned
or things from which there's a negative association, you shouldn't use in
a positive context. So how far do we take that and in
which cases is the גמרא Gemara suggest it in is an interesting
question—why only in certain cases and not others—but that's what we have.
Okay. רבא אמר: Rava amar: אמר קרא וכתב לה, amar kra vechatav
lah, בכתיבה מתגרשת ואינה מתגרשת בכסף. bechtivah mitgareshet ve-einah mitgareshet bechesef. So
רבא Rava has to suggest or reject the notion that a person
could get divorced using money, because the פסוק pasuk says וכתב לה,
vechatav lah, you have to write the גט. get We spent three
months on this. וכתב לה בכתיבה מתגרשת ואינה מתגרשת בכסף. vechatav lah
bechtivah mitgareshet ve-einah mitgareshet bechesef. ואימא בכתיבה מתגרשת ואינה מתקדשת בכתיבה? ve'eima
bechtivah mitgareshet ve-einah mitkadeshet bechtivah? So how come we make that לימוד,
that is, you could get divorced with a גט get but not
divorced with money, and we don't use the same וכתב לה vechatav
lah to learn you can get divorced with a שטר shtar and
not married with a שטר? shtar, The answer: הכתיב ויצאה והיתה מקיש
הויה ליציאה. haktiv veyatzah vehayetah makish havaya liyetziah. We connect קידושין kiddushin
to גירושין, gerushin so that's the question. ומה ראית מסתברא קאי בגירושין
וממעיט גירושין קאי בגירושין וממעיט קידושין? umah ra'ita mistabra kai b'geirushin umama'it
geirushin kai b'geirushin umama'it kiddushin? So why what it's logical to suggest
that when we're making a מיעוט, mi'ut, we're making a reduction on
the possibilities, we would apply from גירושין gerushin to גירושין gerushin and
not גירושין gerushin to קידושין. kiddushin? Now frankly, this has been this
whole back and forth about exactly this question, which is whenever we
have any הלכה halacha that we're trying to learn here through all
these דפים, dappim, are we connecting קידושין kiddushin, to other modes of
קידושין? kiddushin Are we connecting גירושין gerushin to קידושין? kiddushin Are we
connecting גירושין gerushin? to גירושין? gerushin Are we connecting גירושין geirushin, to
קידושין? kiddushin. So those kinds of questions are left somewhat unresolved. I
want to note an interesting מחלוקת machloket brought in the רשב"א. Rashba.
The רשב"א Rashba has a question about could you get married using
קרקע karka or not? We saw there's a problem of מחובר mechubar
by a גט. You cannot write a גט on something which is
still מחובר לקרקע, mechubar lekarka, still attached to the ground, because that's
not really ספר כריתות. sefer kritut. It's not and it has to
be ונתן, so it can't be that it's lacking anything of קציצה
kitzitzah before the נתינה. netinah. So the question is, could you use
a piece of property as your קידושי כסף? kiddushei kesef. And even
could you use a piece of property as perhaps your שטר shtar
קידושין kiddushin. written on a tree or something like that? So the
בעל העיטור Ba'al HaIttur thinks that you could not use קרקע karka
because we say היקש הויה ליציאה. We connect from divorce to marriage.
And the רשב"א Rashba himself actually accepts the idea of using קרקע.
karka. He says look, the only way we connect הויה ליציאה is
to שטר shtar, קידושין. kiddushin. But if we're talking about קידושי כסף,
kiddushei kesef? the money we use for marriage, there are no limitations
on—about מחובר. mechubar. Of course you could give ownership of a piece
of land and transfer that, and that piece of land could serve
as קידושי כסף. kiddushei kessef. So that's an interesting question of how
far do we take those equations? Okay. ואימא וכו'. ve'eima vechu'. Okay.
ולרבי יוסי הגלילי דאפיק ליה להאי קרא לדרשה אחרינא, ul'Rabbi Yose HaGlili
d'afik lei l'hai kra l'drasha achrina, Rabbi Yose HaGlili uses this דרשה,
drasha that is וכתב לה vechatav lah for a different דרשה in
יבמות, Yevamot, sorry, גיטין Gittin on כ"א, kaf aleph, שאינה מתגרשת בכסף,
she'einah mitgareshet bechesef, that she could not get divorced with money. The
money, מנא ליה? mena lei? So how does Rabbi Yose learn that?
אמר קרא, ספר כריתות. sefer kritut. ספר כרתה ואין דבר אחר כרתה.
sefer kartah v'ein davar acher kartah. You could only get divorced using
a book, using a bill, and not any other way. ורבנן האי
כריתות מאי עבדי ליה? v'rabanan hai kritut mai avdi lei? How do
the Rabbis then
understand the fact that it says כריתות kritut and not כרת? karat?
And that's the דרשה that Rabbi Yose uses.
מיבעי ליה לדבר הכורת בינו לבינה. mibaei lei l'davar hakoret beino l'beina.
They require it to learn that it has to be a full
severance at the time of divorce, כדתניא, k'detanya, we saw this a
few weeks ago or last week, about all the different תנאים tna'im
of divorce. הרי זה גיטך על מנת שלא תשתי יין על מנת
שלא תלכי לבית אביך לעולם. harei zeh gitech al m'nat shelo tishti
yayin al m'nat shelo telchi l'veit avich l'olam. If a person makes
a permanent תנאי tnai on the גירושין, he says, this is your
divorce on the condition that you never drink wine ever, אין זה
כריתות, ein zeh kritut, because that cannot be considered כריתות, kritut, that
can't be considered a divorce because his power over her still residual
effect. That is that the תנאי tnai will be binding forever. כל
שלושים יום הרי זה כריתות. kol shloshim yom harei zeh kritut. But
if it's for thirty days then that's binding. The question comes up,
what if it's longer than thirty days and shorter than forever? So
what if he says for fifty years? What if she's sixty years
old and he says for the next fifty years you can't go
visit your parents? Is that the same thing? Is that... So the
רשב"א Rashba deals with that in a תשובה tshuvah and the רשב"א
Rashba thinks even an extended period of time is considered that it
has an end. And תוספות Tosafot deals with that here as well,
the question of the what about if she predeceases him or what
if he predeceases her, how do we consider some of those cases
about דבר הכורת בינו לבינה? davar hakoret beino l'beina? הרי זה גיטך
על מנת שלא תשתי יין על מנת שלא תלכי לבית אביך לעולם
אין זה כריתות כל שלושים יום הרי זה כריתות. harei zeh gitech
al m'nat shelo tishti yayin al m'nat shelo telchi l'veit avich l'olam
ein zeh kritut kol shloshim yom harei zeh kritut. So if it's
for thirty days then it is כריתות. kritut. That is a good
severance. רבי יוסי הגלילי מכרת כריתות קנפקא ליה. Rabbi Yose HaGlili mikarat
kritut k'nafka lei. He learns it out from the fact that the
פסוק could have said the word כרת, karat, ספר כרת, sefer karat,
and it says instead ספר כריתות, sefer kritut, multiple כריתות, kritut, so
he can learn both דרשות from that. ורבנן כרת כריתות לא משמע
להו. v'rabanan karat kritut lo mashma lehu. And the Rabbis do not
learn from the word כרת karat to the word כריתות. kritut. חדא
מחדא לא אתיא. chada mechada lo atya. So why, if we cannot
learn one from one... yeah, Charlie? You were having an אמוראית Amoraic
discussion and then all of a sudden we get תנאים. tanna'im. Well,
we have to address, well it's because we as a loose end
we have to address רבי יוסי הגלילי's Rabbi Yose HaGlili opinion from
גיטין, Gittin, which we had not brought up until now. It's a
good question about the structure of the סוגיא. sugya. Moving forward, we've
just concluded the question of can we learn one to one? The
גמרא Gemara has just said חדא מחדא לא אתיא. chada mechada lo
atya. We cannot derive one from one, that is one of the
ways of getting married from any of the other ones. However, תיתי
חדא מתרתי. teiti chada mitarti. Can we derive one from two at
once? So הי תיתי לא נכתוב רחמנא בשטר. hai teiti lo nictov
rachmana b'shtar. If the תורה had not written that you could get
married with a שטר, shtar, ותיתי מהנך, v'teiti m'hanach, מה להנך שכן
הנאתן מרובה. mah l'hanach sheken hana'atan merubah. So we would say, well
maybe you could derive שטר shtar from the combination of ביאה biah
and כסף. kesef And we say no, no, no, ביאה biah and
כסף kesef are different than שטר shtar because הנאתן מרובה. hana'atan merubah.
ביאה biah and כסף Kesef have a quality that שטר shtar does
not have, which is הנאה. hana'ah. If you get more money or
if you're more sexually active, there is a הנאה hana'ah involved in
that act or in that property, and a שטר shtar there is
no הנאה hana'ah in owning a שטר. shtar A שטר doesn't have
any intrinsic value. We know that the שטר could be פחות משווה
פרוטה. pachot mishaveh pruta. The שטר has no הנאה. hana'ah. All it
is is a legal object. And as a legal object, it has
no הנאה, hana'ah, so that's what's different about שטר from the other
two. We're going to see that each of them has unique qualities.
So the unique quality of שטר is that it does not work
by a transfer of הנאה. hana'ah. There's a question, the שער המלך
Sha'ar HaMelech has a problem about could marriage be effected, could קידושין
kiddushin, be effected through anal sex or not? And there's a question,
חז"ל Chazal at least understand that anal sex involves less הנאה, hana'ah,
and he has a problem about this and he says, well maybe
it's because ביאה biah. actually doesn't work by transfer of הנאה hana'ah
at all. It's actually a legal act of ביאה. biah It's the
מעשה קנין, ma'aseh kinyan, it's the act of קנין kinyan and it's
not because there's some הנאה hana'ah involved in the act. So that's
a question about how much or how little the fact that the
גמרא Gemara says שכן הנאתן מרובה sheken hana'atan merubah is that an
intrinsic quality of the act of ביאה biah that it must have
הנאה hana'ah in order to produce קידושין kiddushin, or not? שכן הנאתן
מרובה. sheken hana'atan merubah. No, I mean, well, yes and no, it
depends who enjoyed it more. Okay, so that's exactly the question. So
the question is here the גמרא Gemara says ביאה biah is different
from שטר in that ביאה biah. has הנאה. hana'ah. Is that intrinsic
to the process of קידושי ביאה biah that there be הנאה hana'ah
transferred from the man to the woman or that the woman experience
some הנאה hana'ah through that process or not? That's the thing. In
general there's הנאה, hana'ah, meaning therefore you... Okay, but so that's the
legal issue is it's irrelevant, your subjectivity of experience is irrelevant to
the legal question of the force of the ביאה. bia Okay, so
we say לא מצית, lo matzit, so what did we just say,
we said what? So מה הנאה שכן הנאתן? mah hana'ah sheken hana'atan?
כסף kesef and ביאה bia have הנאה hana'ah and שטר does not
have. No, no, I'm saying so therefore what? So therefore we cannot
learn from the fact that we have ביאה bia, and כסף Kesef,
that you could not extrapolate from those two that you could also
do קנין שטר. kinyan shtar. That is, we cannot learn חדא מתרתי.
chada mitarti. We cannot learn one out of the two. We're going
to have to derive that one out of those two, and we're
going to see each of the three different methods has its own
unique property, and therefore each of them must be learned out uniquely.
Okay. לא נצריך רחמנא בביאה ותיתי מהנך. Lo nitzreich rachamana bebia veteiti
mehanoch. So couldn't we have not written ביאה bia and we would
have been able to learn it out from these two? That is,
כסף kesef and שטר. מה להנך שכן קניינם מרובה. Mah lanoch shekein
kinyanan merubeh. כסף kesef and שטר have many different things that they
could be used for קניינים. kinyanim. We're going to see the rest
of the פרק perek addresses purchasing land, purchasing slaves. There are other
kinds of transactions which could be effected using כסף kesef and שטר,
but ביאה, bia. ביאה bia is not a normal mode of acquisition.
If you go out to the marketplace, you cannot buy a piece
of land by ביאה. bia It sort of doesn't make sense. תוספות
Tosafot has a suggestion that's rejected, but תוספות Tosafot has a הוה
אמינא hava minah about perhaps we could compare the idea of חזקה
chazakah by קרקע, karka, that is buying a piece of land by
building a fence around it or by plowing it or by walking
along the environs, in some way demonstrating ownership or establishing the connection
to the property as the as the owner of the land. Could
that be comparable in some sense to ביאה bia by קידושין? kiddushin.
You've physically changed something. Well, it's not just physically changed, but it's
a demonstrating the reality of the relationship between the owner and the
field in the same way that a sexual act is a demonstration
of the marital relationship, and תוספות Tosafot rejects that notion. But it's
an interesting question. Obviously it touches on a very sensitive issue about
how much is the woman's role in the sexual act to
be compared or
not to the way a person buys a piece of field, and
that's exactly תוספות's Tosafot objection, which is that you can't compare those
two. They're very different kinds of of legally significant acts. Right, but
if you're saying that it's a way of doing קידושין, kiddushin? then
they're actually quite similar. I don't understand. If you learned from it,
then it does make sense. So, we'll have to see that תוספות
Tosafot inside. It's תוספות Tosafot on דף ג, daf gimmel, and I
think it comes up in this, yeah, it's תוספות Tosafot on דף
ג. daf gimmel. So maybe we can talk about it a little
bit afterwards, but it's a serious question that takes a lot of
time, I think, to address it appropriately. So מה להנך שכן קניינם
מרובה? mah lanoch shekein kinyanan merubeh? לא נצריך רחמנא בכסף, Lo nitzreich
rachamana bekesef, what if the Torah had not mentioned קידושי כסף? kiddushei
kessef. ותיתי מהנך. Veteiti mehanoch. מה להנך שכן ישנן בעל כרחה. Mah
lanoch shekein yeshnan baal korchah. So שטר could be בעל כרחה, baal
korchah, that is some kind of a שטר, in this case the
שטר of divorce, could be בעל כרחה. baal korchah. A husband can
divorce his wife בעל כרחה, baal korchah, without her will, and therefore
we know that שטר, the world of שטר, exists with a possibility
of בעל כרחה. baal korchah. And ביאה bia exists in a world
of בעל כרחה. baal korchah. We saw that the ביאה bia for
יבום, yibum, because the woman has already in some sense, we said
יבום yibum doesn't apply, so יבום yibum as well, the ביאה bia
of יבום yibum could be בעל כרחה, baal korchah, and again it
doesn't mean rape, it means the specific agreement to the legal entry
into the marital relationship with this man does not require her to
agree at this time. That is, her דעת daat for the קידושין
kiddushin. was already, we said this does not apply to normal case
of marriage. And it doesn't apply to a normal case. But what
about so then what happens? So then they'll do, they'll do חליצה.
chalitzah. That's the point. And again, how much does it come out,
it is a gray line there as well and it becomes problematic.
But that's part of the issue here. And the point is that
ביאה bia and שטר could exist as בעל כרחה. baal korchah. But
in some cases. In some cases. They exist in that universe. כסף,
kesef according to the גמרא, Gemara, כסף kesef there's no such thing
as כסף בעל כרחה. kesef baal korchah. תוספות Tosafot of course tells
us there are, well, okay, that's part of the question. The other
question תוספות Tosafot brings is from אמה עברייה. amah ivriyah. The father
can sell his daughter off as an אמה עברייה amah ivriyah בעל
כרחה, baal korchah, and the question then, and תוספות Tosafot develops this
idea and it's a very important idea, which is that the husband's
role, the father's role in the אמה עברייה amah ivriyah and perhaps
in קידושי קטנה kiddushei ketanah in general is not that the father
is doing something against the daughter's will and that he's imposing it
on her. It's actually that he's the active agent at that time.
She's a minor, he's the active legal agent and therefore it's not
בעל כרחה. baal korchah. It's not בעל כרחה baal korchah because she's
not a בר דעת, bar daat, she's not, there's no רצון ratzon
as it were. Right. So the way in which דעת daat is
effected in this transaction comes through the father and so it's not
considered to be בעל כרחה. baal korchah. Okay. שכן ישנן בעל כרחה.
Shekein yeshnan baal korchah. וכי תימא כסף נמי בעל כרחה באמה עברייה.
Vechi teima kesef nami baal korchah beamah ivriyah. So גמרא Gemara asks
this question. Couldn't it be בעל כרחה baal korchah by אמה עברייה?
amah ivriyah? And it says באישות מיהא לא אשכחן. beishut mi lo
ashkechan. It's not אישות. ishut. Right. אמה העבריה *amah ha'ivriya* even though
it has certain marital aspects, that is through ייעוד *yi'ud*, the primary
role of אמה העבריה *amah ha'ivriya* is in fact not anything to
do with marriage at all. אמר רב הונא Rav Huna's... *Amar Rav
Huna*: חופה קונה מקל וחומר chuppah koneh mikal vachomer, *chuppa koneh m'kal
vachomer*. So we have finished our discussion of the three ways of
getting married, that is כסף kesef. *kesef*, שטר *shtar*, and ביאה bia?
*biah*. We saw that each of them has its own לימוד *limmud*,
we saw that none of them could be derived from any of
the other ones. And then we said, well maybe we could derive
one from two, and we said no, each of them has a
unique quality. שטר *shtar* has no הנאה hana'ah? *hana'ah*, ביאה bia *biah*
has no קניינים kinyanim *kinyanim* generally, it's not a normal way of
making קניינים kinyanim *kinyanim*, and כסף kesef *kesef* it does not exist
בעל כרחו *bal korcho*. It's unique in that aspect. So each of
the different ways of getting married has different mechanism or different properties
that is really interesting to think about how the fact that three
different processes to all reach the same ends could have drastically different
tenor, drastically different qualities, and it actually raises important and significant aspects
of the fact that nowadays we all use קידושי כסף kesef? *kiddushei
kesef* and not any of the other modes of קידושין kiddushin *kiddushin*.
It's interesting to consider the fact that each of them even though
they reach the same legal end actually are very different processes. So
רב הונא Rav Huna *Rav Huna* now suggests what about חופה chuppah
*chuppa*? חופה chuppah? *chuppa* we know is the rabbinic term for נישואין
nissuin. *nisuin*, for the process, the second stage of marriage. And חופה
chuppah? *chuppa*, the ראשונים *rishonim* have I think a seven-way מחלוקת machloket
*machloket* about what חופה chuppah. *chuppa* actually refers to. Does it refer
to wrapping the two people together in some kind of a בגד
*beged* like you see at some ספרדי *Sephardi* weddings where they wear
a טלית *tallit* together? Does it refer to spreading a sheet over
them like אשכנזי *Ashkenazi* weddings we often do? That's the חופה chuppah
*chuppa*. Does it refer to the husband putting a cloth over the
wife's face? That's the veiling process. Does it refer to ייחוד *yichud*?
Does it refer to sex? There are many different... does it refer
to going home to the house that they will live in together
and eating there or living there? So each of those different processes
are obviously going to tell us what this חופה chuppah. *chuppa* is
about. It's a big מחלוקת machlokes *machloket*. So אמר רב הונא Rav
Huna. *Amar Rav Huna*: חופה קונה מקל וחומר chuppah koneh mikal vachomer,
*chuppa koneh m'kal vachomer*. We should say that חופה chuppah *chuppa* could
effect the קניין kinyan? *kinyan* of קידושין kiddushin *kiddushin* by a קל
וחומר kal v'chomer. *kal vachomer*. You mean that there's no basis for
a חופה chuppah *chuppa* in the תורה *Torah*? The תורה *Torah* knows
of נישואין nissuin *nisuin* and therefore חופה chuppah *chuppa* just means נישואין
nissuin. *nisuin*. חופה chuppah. *chuppa* is the rabbinic word for the second
stage of marriage. So רב הונא Rav Huna's *Rav Huna* says חופה
chuppah קונה koneh מקל וחומר *chuppa koneh m'kal vachomer*. חופה chuppah *chuppa*
could even effect קידושין kiddushin *kiddushin*. Why? חופה chuppah קונה מקל וחומר
ומה כסף kessef, שאינו מאכיל בתרומה קונה חופה chuppah שמאכלת בתרומה אינו
דין שתקנה *chuppa koneh m'kal vachomer umah kesef she'eino ma'achil b'terumah koneh
chuppa she'ma'achelet b'terumah eino din she'tikneh*. So couldn't we say that because
a חופה chuppah *chuppa* allows a married woman to eat תרומה *terumah*
if she married a כהן kohen *kohen*, then so that should prove
that חופה chuppah. *chuppa* is actually better at effecting the marital state
than even the other methods of קידושין kiddushin, *kiddushin* which do not
allow her to eat תרומה *terumah*. Good one. וכי כסף kessef? אינו
מאכיל *v'chi kesef eino ma'achil*? So how do we know... so that's
a question. Does כסף kessef. *kesef* not allow her to eat תרומה
*terumah*? And this is a question that comes up all across ש"ס
*Shas* which is at what point does a married woman who marries
a כהן kohen *kohen*, when is she allowed to eat תרומה *terumah*?
Is it from קידושין kiddushin. *kiddushin* or only from נישואין nissuin, *nisuin*?
רב הונא Rav Huna *Rav Huna's* suggestion is that it's only from
נישואין nissuin *nisuin*. The גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is going to quote a
position that it is from the time of קידושין kiddushin *kiddushin*, at
least מדאורייתא *m'deoraisa*. That is וכי כסף אינו מאכיל והאמר עולא דבר
תורה ארוסה בת ישראל אוכלת בתרומה *v'chi kesef eino ma'achil v'ha amar
Ulla devar Torah arusa bat Yisrael ochelet b'terumah*. A woman who's only
מקודשת mekudeshet *mekudeshet* could eat תרומה *terumah* מדאורייתא *m'deoraisa*. Why? שנאמר וכהן
כי יקנה נפש קניין כספו kinyan kaspo, *shenemar v'kohen ki yikne nefesh
kinyan kaspo*. And since the marital relationship is effected as קניין kinyan
כספו *kinyan kaspo*, that is one of the ways of doing קידושין
kiddushin. *kiddushin*, so therefore the wife could eat תרומה *terumah* even from
the time of marriage. והאי קניין kinyan כספו הוא *v'hai kinyan kaspo
hu*. She's קניין kinyan כספו *kinyan kaspo*. She has been acquired by
his money. ומה טעם אמרו אינה אוכלת *u'mah ta'am amru einah ochelet*?
מדרבנן *miderabbanan* a woman who is מקודשת mekudeshet *mekudeshet* cannot eat תרומה
*terumah*. Why? גזירה שמא ימזגו לה כוס בבית אביה ותשקהו לאחיה ולאחיותיה
*gezeira shema yimzegu lah kos b'veit aviha v'tashkeihu l'acheiha v'l'achayoteiha*. Maybe she'll
share the תרומה *terumah*. So she's allowed to eat תרומה *terumah* but
none of her family is, they're not married to כהנים *kohanim*, especially
her male relatives. And therefore, she might share the תרומה *terumah* with
her male relatives or even her female relatives who are not married
to כהנים *kohanim* and they'll come to be serious problems and serious
violations. אלא פריך הכי ומה כסף שאינו גומר קונה חופה chuppah, שגומרת
אינו דין שתקנה *ela parich hachi umah kesef she'eino gomer koneh chuppa
she'gomeret eino din she'tikneh*. ומה כסף שאינו גומר קונה *u'mah kesef she'eino
gomer koneh*. כסף *kesef* which does not complete the marriage, that is
כסף *kesef* can only do קידושין kiddushin. *kiddushin* but not נישואין nissuin
*nisuin*, קונה *koneh* and it does effect קידושין kiddushin. *kiddushin*. חופה chuppah,
שגומרת *chuppa she'gomeret*, חופה chuppah *chuppa* which does effect the second stage
of marriage, it does effect נישואין nissuin, *nisuin*, אינו דין שתקנה *eino
din she'tikneh*? Could it not by קל וחומר kal v'chomer, *kal vachomer*
effect the קידושין kiddushin *kiddushin* as well? מה לכסף שכן פודים בו
הקדש ומעשר שני *mah l'kesef sheken podin bo hekdesh u'ma'aser sheni*. No,
כסף *kesef* is different. כסף *kesef* creates a different kind of a
category. That is כסף *kesef* can do קידושין kiddushin? *kiddushin*, כסף *kesef*
can do מעשר שני ma'aser sheni, *ma'aser sheni*. חופה chuppah *chuppa*, of
course, you would try to do a חופה chuppah *chuppa* with your
מעשר שני ma'aser sheni *ma'aser sheni*, it's not going to פודה *podeh*
the מעשר שני *ma'aser sheni*. That's just a category error. So ביאה
bia תוכח *biah tochiach*. ביאה bia תוכח *biah tochiach* that ביאה bia
*biah* will be the distinguishing characteristic. מה ל... מה לביאה שכן קונה
ביבמה. konah b'yevamah, And ביאה bia can create a קניין kinyan that
is the first stage of marriage by יבמה, yevamah, כסף יוכיח, kesef
yochiach, wait, why are we bringing ביאה bia here? What's it have
to do? What's it going to do? That is maybe we could
prove not from כסף because כסף we rejected because of מעשר שני,
maybe
we can suggest from ביאה? bia Mean ביאה bia works and certainly
חופה chuppah will work? And but ביאה bia is different. Don't some
people say that ביאה bia is חופה? chuppah? What do you do
about those? Exactly. That's exactly the problem. And that's why we said
ביאה שכן קונה ביבמה. bia sheken konah b'yevamah. That why did we
think that because ביאה bia works in יבמה yevamah it should
also work as a חופה? chuppah That is that if we're trying
to learn a קל וחומר
kal v'chomer from one of the
modes of קידושין kiddushin, to חופה. chuppah That is חופה chuppah works
better than קידושין. kiddushin. So ביאה bia we know effects נישואין. nissuin
So ביאה bia also we're trying to compare ביאה bia to חופה.
chuppah And the קל וחומר kal vachomer. is saying because ביאה bia
does חופה chuppah then חופה chuppah, will work as a קניין? kinyan
Right.
Because we know that ביאה is קונה ביבמה, so כסף יוכיח וחזר
הדין. kesef yochiach v'hazar hadin. So each of them has flaws
that neither of them can match up with, but we say לא
ראי זה כראי זה ולא ראי זה כראי זה, lo rai zeh
k'rai zeh v'lo rai zeh k'rai zeh, they each of them has
problems but they're not the same problems. הצד השווה שבהן שקונין בעלמא,
hatzad hashaveh shebahen shekonin b'alma, they could work to effect קניינים in
general, that is ביאה could be used as a קניין קידושין kinyan
kiddushin or ביאה could be used as a קניין kinyan? for יבום,
yibum, and כסף could be used as a קניין for מעשר שני
or it could be used as קניין for קידושין. So קניין בעלמא
וקונה כאן, kinyan b'alma v'koneh kan, and they could make a קניין
קידושין. kinyan kiddushin. מה לצד השווה שבהן שכן שקונין בעלמא וקונה כאן
אף אני אביא חופה שקונין בעלמא וקונה כאן. mah l'tzad hashaveh shebahen
sheken shekonin b'alma v'koneh kan af ani avi chuppah shekonin b'alma v'koneh
kan. We know that it works as a קניין and it should
work as a קניין here as well. ומה לצד השווה שבהן שכן
הנאה מרובה? u'mah l'tzad hashaveh shebahen sheken hana'ah merubah? So what about
ביאה and כסף that have הנאה? hana'ah So and then that should
be a problem for חופה because there's no הנאה hana'ah by חופה.
So שטר יוכיח. shtar yochiach. שטר is just like חופה in that
there's no הנאה and it should still work. מה לשטר שכן מוציא.
mah l'shtar sheken motzi. No, שטר is unique because שטר can be
used for divorce and there's no such thing as using a חופה
for a divorce. שכן מוציא בבת ישראל. sheken motzi b'vas Yisrael. It
could be used to divorce a Jewish divorce. That is important to
note that non-Jewish divorce is just severance of the relationship. The רמב"ם
Rambam has that in הלכות מלכים Hilchot Melachim in פרק ט', perek
tet, people should see that there. כסף וביאה יוכיח וחזר הדין, kesef
u'bia yochiach v'hazar hadin, and ביאה is different because ביאה could not
be used to effect divorce obviously. You could never imagine a relationship
that is ended by a sexual act. So ביאה יוכיח כסף וביאה
יוכיח וחזר הדין, bia yochiach kesef u'bia yochiach v'hazar hadin, לא ראי
זה כראי זה ולא ראי זה כראי זה, lo rai zeh k'rai
zeh v'lo rai zeh k'rai zeh, they each have problems but they
don't have the same problems. הצד השווה שבהן שקונין בעלמא וקונה כאן,
hatzad hashaveh shebahen shekonin b'alma v'koneh kan, they could be used as
קניינים in general and they're קונה here, אף אני אביא חופה שקונין
בעלמא וקונה כאן. af ani avi chuppah shekonin b'alma v'koneh kan. And
that's רב הונא... Rav Huna מה לצד השווה שבהן שכן ישנן בעל
כרחה. mah l'tzad hashaveh shebahen sheken yeshnan b'al karchah. No, each of
those three, I mean, sorry, each of those two, that is שטר
and ביאה could be בעל כרחה b'al karchah and not כסף. ורב
הונא כסף מי הא באישה לא אשכחן בעל כרחה? v'Rav Huna kesef
mi ha b'isha lo ashkechan b'al karchah? And רב הונא Rav Huna...
cannot address the fact that כסף does not exist in a marital
context which is בעל כרחה. b'al karchah. So אמר רבא שתי תשובות
בדבר. amar Rava shtei teshuvot b'davar. So רבא Rava has two problems
for רב הונא. Rav Huna חדא דשלש תנן
ולא ארבע, chada d'shalosh tnan
v'lo arba, the משנה Mishna said האישה נקנית בשלוש דרכים, ha'isha nikneit
b'shalosh drachim, women can get married in two, three ways and not
four ways. ועוד כלום חופה גומרת אלא על ידי קידושין. v'od klum
chuppah gomeret ela al yedei kiddushin. חופה only works to create נישואין
nissuin if it's following קידושין. That's the best problem with רב הונא
Rav Huna. קל וחומר. kal vachomer That is, you want to say
that חופה works because it creates a more expanded קניין? No, חופה
does the second stage of a developing marital relationship. Well, that's exactly
what he's trying to prove. Except רב הונא Rav Huna thinks it
works. Right. So רבא Rava thinks רב הונא Rav Huna is... I
also want to ask you a simple question. Does anybody ask why
that פסוק that was at the bottom of the previous עמוד amud
לגבי כהן l'gabbei kohen could be like a fabulous scriptural source for
כסף? How come that's not the פסוק that's brought? It's addressed in
כתובות Ketubot that primarily that פסוק is talking about actually slaves and
that's part of the קניין כספו, and particularly in the פשט, p'shat,
קניין כספו יליד ביתו מקנת כספו. kinyan kaspo yelid beito miknat kaspo.
There are two kinds of slaves you could own: you could own
a slave who's born to a slave you already own, or you
could have bought a slave. So the context is... you used the
context to simply narrow the focus of the... well, not just narrowing
the focus, but frankly to distinguish between slavery and marriage, which are
very different kinds of קניין כסף. kinyan kesef. It does get brought
up particularly in the גמרא Gemara in כתובות Ketubot and תוספות Tosafot
in כתובות Ketubot deals with that exact distinction, which is that marriage
and slavery are very different. Okay. So חופה גומרת אלא על ידי
קידושין, chuppah gomeret ela al yedei kiddushin, וכי גמירי חופה שלא על
ידי קידושין מחופה שעל ידי קידושין? v'chi gamiri chuppah shelo al yedei
kiddushin mechuppah sheal yedei kiddushin? Does this mean that רב הונא... Rav
Huna רב הונא Rav Huna, thinks that he has a very elaborate,
twisty, confusing kind of קל וחומר, kal vachomer, which is that if
we take all three kinds of קידושין, we can make a קל
וחומר kal vachomer with חופה. That is, each of the three different
ways of getting מקדשת... mekudeshet... Each of the three different ways of
getting מקודשת are each different, but when combined they can do קידושין,
חופה, and they cannot do נישואין. חופה, which can do נישואין, cannot
do- of course should be able to do קידושין. This is- this
is קל וחומר. kal vachomer Yes. And then רבא Rava comes and
says: two problems. Number one, the משנה. The משנה said you can
get married three ways, not four ways. Number two, what are you
talking about חופה can do נישואין קל וחומר kal vachomer it should
be able to do קידושין? There's no such thing. They're two different
processes. And that's exactly רבא's Rava question. So you're going to say,
כלום חופה גומרת אלא על ידי קידושין. klum chuppah gomeret ella al
yedei kiddushin. חופה can only do גמר, gmar, that is the second
act of marriage after קידושין. הכי גמרי חופה שלא על ידי קידושין
מחופה שעל ידי קידושין? hechi gamrei chuppah shelo al yedei kiddushin mechuppah
she'al yedei kiddushin? אמר ליה אביי, Amar lei Abaye, הא- ha so
אביי Abaye is going to defend רב הונא. Rav Huna, הא דקאמר
שלוש תנן ולא ארבע, ha dekamar shalosh tnan velo arba, the fact
that the משנה says three and not four, תנא מילתא דכתיבא בהדיא
קתני מילתא דלא כתיבא בהדיא לא קתני. tana milta dechtiva behedya katanei
milta delo chtiva behedya lo katanei. It only listed the three that
could be learned from the פסוקים. So it's תנא ושייר, tana veshayer,
but it's particularly the difference between things which are mentioned more explicitly
in the תורה compared to something learned from קל וחומר, kal vachomer,
which is entirely logical. Which wasn't a good question and it's not
exactly a good answer either. ודקאמר כלום חופה גומרת אלא על ידי
קידושין רב הונא נמי הכי קאמר. udekamar klum chuppah gomeret ella al
yedei kiddushin Rav Huna nami hechi ka'amar. רב הונא Rav Huna, can
incorporate your challenge to his קל וחומר kal vachomer into the קל
וחומר and make it even more convoluted. מה כסף שאינו גומר אחר
כסף קונה. ma kessef she'eino gomer achar kessef koneh. Money cannot do
נישואין after you have done קידושי כסף. That is, you give money
for קידושין and then you try to give a second ring for
נישואין, it would not work. חופה שגומרת אחר כסף אינו דין שתקנה.
chuppah shegomeret achar kessef eino din shetikneh. רב הונא's Rav Huna קל
וחומר is that since חופה works after כסף, shouldn't חופה work after
חופה? This gets into the תוספות הראש's Tosafot HaRosh question, which is
when רב הונא says חופה קונה מקל וחומר,
does he mean doing חופה once or twice? תוספות הראש Tosafot HaRosh
says, when I say חופה קונה מקל וחומר, does that mean חופה
נישואין עושה, chuppah nissuin oseh, it does both together, or does it
mean חופה would do the קידושין and then you need to do
נישואין afterwards? So that's a major problem with this whole back and
forth. תנו רבנן. Tanu rabanan. Okay, wait, but meanwhile it does stand,
we tried to challenge- רב הונא, we don't פוסק posken by רב
הונא, it seems. We never do. We almost never do. I mean,
why not? He has his קל וחומר, it's very convoluted and it's
rejected by רבא. Rava. But אביי Abaye can deflect רבא's Rava challenges
with weak answers. And frankly, we have מחלוקת אביי ורבא, machloket Abaye
veRava, so we פוסק posken by רבא. Rava. So ממה נפשך- mima
nafshach wait, I don't understand, how was it so weak? It seems
like the גמרא Gemara's didn't challenge אביי's Abaye: rejection of- okay, so
the רי"ף Rif it seems may פוסק posken like רב הונא, and
there are certain בריסקרס Briskers who for whatever reason, there was a
case- I remember there was a case that came up, it maybe
was a hypothetical case, but I'm not sure. There was a כהן
who they had done the באדעקן bedeken and then his wife at
the wedding died of
some kind
of a heart attack or something immediately at that point at the
wedding. Is the כלה kallah died at the wedding? Is the כהן
allowed to be מטמא לה?
mitamei lah? Does- do we say that the חופה that he did
with the veil counts as נישואין or not to allow him to
sit שבעה shiva for her and everything else or not? That was
the question. So that kind of case does not come up so
often, thank God, and there are very few נפקא מינהs nafka mina
with this kind of שיטה. shita. We were not trying to do
קידושין with a חופה anyway.
The question becomes more sort of how much theoretically do we even
consider this notion?
This קל וחומר is very convoluted, it kind of undermines the whole
unique nature of each of the three different modes of
קידושין,
it's kind of extracted by force almost without really an eye to
the nuance. So that's part of why רבא Rava is uncomfortable with
it. But certainly, I forget now whether the רי"ף Rif פוסקs posken
by רב הונא or not. I think I remember that he does.
You'd have to- so you have to intend to do חופה as-
right, you would have to say הרי את מקודשת לי בחופה זו.
harei at mekudeshet li bechuppah zu. We're going to see now exactly
this question, which is the role that the אמירה, amira, that is
verbal declaration, plays in the act of קידושין. So let's continue. תנו
רבנן. Tanu rabanan. כיצד בכסף? keitzad bechessef? How do you get married
with כסף? So we already derived that there is קידושי כסף. Now
we have to deal with what's the process? And this is very
important, which is: נתן לה כסף או שוה כסף ואמר לה הרי
את מקודשת לי הרי את מאורסת לי הרי את לי לאינתו. natan
lah kessef o shaveh kessef ve'amar lah harei at mekudeshet li harei
at me'ureset li harei at li le'intu. You are מקודשת to me,
you are sanctified to me, you are מאורסת, me'ureset, married to me,
הרי את לי לאינתו, harei at li le'intu, you are my wife.
הרי זו מקודשת. harei zu mekudeshet. Then she is married. But you
have to say something. If you just gave it to her and
didn't say anything- so that's exactly the point,
which is that קידושין must be
accompanied by an act of אמירה. amira. Interestingly, there's a distinction by
קידושי שטר. kiddushei shtar Do we say קידושי שטר kiddushei shtar. requires
אמירה amira or not? It's a מחלוקת machlokes. between the רש"י Rashi
we have on our pages and the רש"י Rashi in the back,
רש"י Rashi on the page of the רי"ף. Rif. So we'll maybe
get to that when we talk about קידושי שטר. Do you give
her the ring and let's say, like let's say the modern way
we do it, and you say, "Will you marry me?" So we're
going to deal with exactly that question coming up, which is under
what circumstances are these things expendable? That is, the fundamental quality is
the transfer of כסף. The question of how crucial the אמירה amira
is is going to come up in just a sec. אבל היא
שנתנה ואמרה היא, aval hi she-natnah ve-amrah hi, what if she gives
the ring to him and she says? What does she say? הריני
מקודשת לך, hareini mekudeshet lach, I am married to you, הריני מאורסת
לך, hareini me'ureset lach, הריני לך לאינתו, hareini lach le-into, אינה מקודשת.
eina mekudeshet. She would not be married in that case. Now what
happened? We changed two things. That's the גמרא's Gemara problem. We changed
the fact that he did not give the ring, she gave the
ring, and we changed the fact that she said something and he
did not say something. מתקיף לה רב פפא, matkif lah Rav Pappa,
רב פפא Rav Pappa has a problem with this ברייתא. braisa. טעמא
דנתן הוא ואמר הוא, הא נתן הוא ואמרה היא אינה מקודשת. ta'ama
de-natan hu ve-amar hu, ha natan hu ve-amrah hi eina mekudeshet. Would
you say the reason it works is because he gave the ring
and he said it and therefore if she... What about the middle
case? What about if he gives the ring and she says something?
So with that you would say אינה מקודשת? eina mekudeshet? אימא סיפא,
eima seifa, אבל היא שנתנה לו ואמרה היא, לא הוי קידושין, aval
hi she-natnah lo ve-amrah hi, lo havei kiddushin, then they're not married.
טעמא דנתנה היא ואמרה היא, הא נתן הוא ואמרה היא הוו קידושין,
ta'ama de-natnah hi ve-amrah hi, ha
natan hu ve-amrah hi havei kiddushin, then it would work. So רב
פפא Rav Pappa doesn't know. רב פפא Rav Pappa asks the question.
רישא דווקא, reisha davka, so the גמרא Gemara concludes רישא דווקא, reisha
davka, the beginning of the ברייתא braisa is precise. That is, the
man has to do both for it to be קידושין. סיפא כדי
נסבה, seifa kedi nasba, and the סיפא seifa just came along for
the ride. That is, use a similar formulation for mnemonic purposes. ותני
סיפא מילתא דסתר לה לרישא, ve-tanei seifa milta de-satra leh le-reisha, but
no, it's not just that it came along for the ride, it
actually says something that contradicts. אלא הכי קאמר, ella hachi ka'amar, נתן
הוא ואמר הוא פשיטא דהוו קידושין. natan hu ve-amar hu peshita de-havei
kiddushin. If he gives the money and he says it, that for
sure works for קידושין. נתן הוא ואמרה היא נעשה כמי שנתנה היא
ואמרה היא ולא הוו קידושין. natan hu ve-amrah hi na'aseh ke-mi she-natnah
hi ve-amrah hi ve-lo havei kiddushin. That's like she gave it. The
fact that she said something when he gave it makes it like
she gave it. That's what the גמרא says. ולא הוו קידושין, ve-lo
havei kiddushin, and it would not be קידושין. איבעית אימא, ibayis eima,
alternatively, נתן הוא ואמר הוא מקודשת, natan hu ve-amar hu mekudeshet, נתנה
היא ואמרה היא אינה מקודשת, natnah hi ve-amrah hi eina mekudeshet, if
she does both it does not work. However, נתן הוא ואמרה היא
ספקא היא וחיישינן מדרבנן. natan hu ve-amrah hi sefeka hi ve-chaishinan mi-derabbanan.
Maybe that's ספק קידושין. safek kiddushin. That is, if the man gives
the woman the ring and the woman says something, the man doesn't
say anything, he's silent, does her אמירה amira play the role of
the אמירה amira or not? That's ספק קידושין. safek kiddushin. The first
opinion is that it's in fact would not be קידושין at all.
Second opinion is חיישינן מדרבנן. chaishinan mi-derabbanan. That is, if she would
go and now and marry a second man, she would require to
divorce both of them. So that's an important question about the role
of the אמירה, amira, that is, what role does the verbal declaration
play at the time of קידושין? The woman participating in the verbal
declaration could actively undermine even a kosher נתינה, netina, the man giving
the ring. So that's important to note, it has to do with
the fact of what's the process here?
The פסוק says כי יקח איש אשה, ki yikach ish isha, the
man takes the wife, obviously the man based on that פסוק was
going to have a more active role in the process than the
woman. But to what extent? Or what role? Again, the אמירה amira
is not mentioned in the פסוק at all. So why would the
woman's participation in that way undermine or compromise the process is an
important question. There we have two alternatives here. This still doesn't answer
my question, which was sort of intermediate, like, you know, "will you
marry me?" right? So it's not him saying "you will be married..."
right? Okay, so that's going to come up, I think in tomorrow's
דף daf or maybe it's in two days. The question of עסוקים
באותו ענין. asukim be-oto inyan. What if they're involved in the process,
they're both standing under the חופה, what if they don't say anything?
So that probably works anyway. But it's an interesting question. We're going
to see here right now שמואל, Shmuel, the opinion about ידיים. yadayim.
So we remember back to נדרים Nedarim at the beginning of last
summer, נדרים Nedarim and נזיר, Nazir, we have a principle of ידיים.
yadayim. That is, you don't say the exact proper formulation, you say
something similar, something that implies it. There are ידיים מוכיחות, yadayim mochi'chos,
it's obvious what you meant, there are ידיים שאינן מוכיחות yadayim she-einan
mochi'chos that are not obvious what you meant, and then there are
things which are so unclear that they're not even ידיים yadayim at
all. There's a מחלוקת about ידיים שאינן מוכיחות, yadayim she-einan mochi'chos, ידיים
yadayim which are not explicit, do we say הוי ידיים havi yadayim
or not? That is, if I see a נזיר nazir walking by
and I say "aha, like that one," does that make me a
נזיר nazir or not? That's a מחלוקת. So we're going to see:
אמר שמואל בקידושין, amar Shmuel be-kiddushin, in a case of קידושין, נתן
לה כסף או שוה כסף natan lah kessef o shaveh kessef ואמר
הרי את מקודשת, ve-amar harei at mekudeshet, "you are married," or
הרי את מאורסת, harei at me'ureset, הרי את לאינתו, harei at le-into,
"you are to me for a wife," he does not say לי.
li. So הרי זו מקודשת, harei zo mekudeshet, so she's married to
him, presumably. הריני אישיך הריני בעליך הריני ארוסיך, hareini isheich, hareini ba'aleich,
hareini aruseich, I am your husband, אין כאן בית מיחוש, ein kan
beis michush, that there's nothing even to be worried about in that
case. That means not קידושין. The man says, "I am your husband,"
because the man's status does not change. The woman's status is what
changes. She goes from being unmarried to being someone with whom no
other man could have a relationship with.
She needs a גט from this man in order to remarry, all
sorts of things. The woman's status is what changes. There is no
status that the man attains. The man could go and marry another
wife. No, but isn't it implicit? I am giving you this so
that I would be your husband, and obviously with that, you'll be
my wife. And that's proof that שמואל Shmuel does not hold by
ידיים. yadayim. So let's... we're going to exactly see that. So אין
כאן בית מיחוש, ein kan beis michush, that's what שמואל Shmuel says.
וכן בגירושין שנתן לה ואמר לה הרי את משולחת הרי את מגורשת
הרי את מותרת לכל אדם הרי זו מגורשת. vechein b'gerushin she-nasan lah
v'amar lah harei at meshulachat harei at megureshet harei at muteret l'chol
adam harei zu megureshet. If you say, "You're sent away," "You're divorced,"
then she is divorced. איני אישיך איני בעליך איני ארוסיך אין כאן
בית מיחוש. eini ishech eini baalech eini arusech ein kan beis michush.
That's not a divorce. If you say, "I'm not your husband anymore,"
that isn't a divorce. אמר ליה רב פפא לאביי, amar lei Rav
Pappa l'Abaye, רב פפא Rav Pappa said to אביי: למימר דסבר שמואל
ידיים שאינן מוכיחות הויין ידיים? l'meimar d'savar Shmuel yadayim she-einan mochi-chos havyan
yadayim? שמואל Shmuel thinks ידיים yadayim which are not obvious are are
good ידיים. yadayim. That is, we say as long as he said
הרי את מקודשת, harei at mekudeshet, that is enough. He didn't say
מקודשת לי, mekudeshet li, so that's ידיים שאינן מוכיחות הויין ידיים. yadayim
she-einan mochi-chos havyan yadayim. והתנן האמר אהא, ve-hasnan ha-amar aha, if he
says about this נזיר, nazir, הרי זה נזיר. harei zeh nazir. He
just said אהא, aha, like this one, he is a נזיר. nazir.
והוינן בה ודילמא אהא בתענית קאמר? ve-havinan bah ve-dilma aha b'ta'anis ka-amar?
Maybe he meant he would adopt a fast and not that he
was trying to become a נזיר nazir קאמר? ka-amar? ואמר שמואל והוא
שהיה נזיר עובר לפניו. ve-amar Shmuel ve-hu she-hayah nazir over le-fanav. It
only works if the נזיר nazir was actually right in front of
him. And therefore טעמא דנזיר עובר לפניו הוא, ta'ama de-nazir over le-fanav
hu, לאו הכי לא. lav hachi lo. If the נזיר nazir were
not walking past at that time, then he would not be a
נזיר. nazir. אוקיי, Okay, says הכא במאי עסקינן, hacha b'mai askinan, אמר
ליה: amar lei: אי הכי מאי קא משמע לן הני לישני בתראי
קא משמע לן? ei hachi mai kamashma lan hanni lishnei batrai kamashma
lan? So either it's because of the you said לי li or
אי הכי מאי קא משמע לן הני לישני בתראי קא משמע לן?
ei hachi mai kamashma lan hanni lishnei batrai kamashma lan? It comes
to teach all the later לישני בתראי, lishnei batrai, the later formulations
that is said about אין כאן בית מיחוש, ein kan beis michush,
that if the man tries to teach his... to change his status,
that it doesn't work. That's what שמואל Shmuel came to teach and
not to teach us anything about ידיים. yadayim. קא משמע לן הכא
כתיב כי יקח ולא שיקח את עצמו. kamashma lan hacha kesiv ki
yikach v'lo she-yikach es atzmo. He has to change the woman's status
and not change his own status. לא יקח את עצמו. lo yikach
es atzmo. He cannot take himself to her. והכא כתיב ושלחה ולא
שישלח את עצמו. ve-hacha kesiv v'shilchah v'lo she-yishlach es atzmo. He has
to divorce her and not that he divorces himself from her. That
is, the woman's status is the one that changes and not the
man's.